Guide to the Lyle M. Nelson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lyle M. Nelson papers
1961-1991
1961-1977
SC0989
Nelson, Lyle M.
1 Linear feet
This matierials primarily pertain to Nelson's work as director of university relations and includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, articles, and other materials. Subjects include academic freedom and the H. Bruce Franklin case, issues pertaining to plans for the Ladera Dam, the indirect cost controversy of 1991, and the independence of the STANFORD DAILY and the 1977 legal case of Zurcher v. Stanford. Correspondence is largely congratulatory on Nelson’s career at Stanford, but does include other issues. There are also materials on the White House Conference on Education in 1965 that Nelson helped to organize.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This materials are open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Nelson, emeritus professor of communication at the time of his death in 1997, came to Stanford in 1961 as director of university relations. In 1968 he became executive head of the department of communication and served as the department's chairman from 1972 to 1979. He was named the Thomas M. Storke Distinguished Professor of Communication in 1973. In the early 1970s, Nelson helped raise funds to back the STANFORD DAILY's protest of a Palo Alto police raid on its offices, a case the DAILY lost in the U.S. Supreme Court. In 1984, Nelson won the Kenneth M. Cuthbertson Award, Stanford's highest honor for exceptional service to the university.
Description of the Collection
This materials primarily pertain to Nelson's work as director of university relations and includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, clippings, articles, and other materials. Subjects include academic freedom and the H. Bruce Franklin case, issues pertaining to plans for the Ladera Dam, the indirect cost controversy of 1991, and the independence of the STANFORD DAILY and the 1977 legal case of Zurcher v. Stanford. Correspondence is largely congratulatory on Nelson’s career at Stanford, but does include other issues. There are also materials on the White House Conference on Education in 1965 that Nelson helped to organize.
Access Terms
Franklin, H. Bruce (Howard Bruce), 1934-; Nelson, Lyle M.; Academic freedom.; Ladera Dam (Calif.)
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Academic Freedom statements 1962-65 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology of SU events Feb. 1969-Feb. 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, largely congratulatory with a few clippings, 1968-72 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, congratulatory and miscellaneous, 1971-73 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Educational reform, articles and clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - H. Bruce Franklin case – clippings, press releases, statements, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indirect cost controversy clippings 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Indirect cost controversy press releases, statements, articles, 1990-91 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jokes and hoaxes [press release parodies] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ladera Dam materials (1 of 2) 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ladera Dam materials (2 of 2) 1961-62 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photograph of Nelson with Bob Beyers and Bruce Bliven (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pitzer (Kenneth), several press releases and a letter, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pitzer – Lyman transition (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Stanford Daily independence, clippings and articles, 1969-70 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - USOE Educational Relations Program – report and correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - White House Conference on Education 1965 – publications (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - White House Conference on Education 1965 – correspondence 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - White House Conference on Education 1965 – clippings, panel handouts, and a few letters (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Young, Howard, "At Stanford University Even the Bad News Is Fit to Print," USIS feature, September 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Zurcher v. Stanford Daily, legal documents, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)